Luis Guillermo Natera Orozco

Data Analyst

natera@hey.com luisnatera.com +31-6-15-58-64-98 GitHub.com/NateraLuis Linkedin.com/in/Natera

Motivated, interdisciplinarity team-work oriented, and responsible Data Analyst with significant experience working in urban mobility and data analysis. Highly educated, Ph.D. in Network Science from the Central European University. Besides my academic background I have developed in different industry positions working across sectors developing python algorithms to, among others, measure urban liveability, analyse investment decisions, and understand consumers behaviors. I am interested in data science and data analysis as a driver to have an impact in businesses and society.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Data management

PostgreSQL, PostGIS, Data Analysis, Pattern & Trend Identification, Data Visualization, Data wrangling with Python

Computational tools

Python (+5 years experience), Jupyter Notebooks & Jupyter Lab stack, GeoPython stack (GeoPandas, MovingPandas, Kepler, H3, OSMnx, Google Maps API), Sci-kit learn, Django (intermediate), HTML (intermediate), CSS (intermediate), Javascript (beginner), SQL (intermediate), ETeX(intermediate), Git + {GitHub, GitLab, Bitbucket}, Ci/Cd, AWS (RDS, S3, EC2), Tableau (intermediate)

Research methods

Urban planning, Network & Data science research methodologies, Data mining, Statistical analysis

WORK EXPERIENCE

SYSTEMIQ

Associate / Python modeler 12/2021 -

Analytics Hub

Python devleoper Implementation of GitHub template repository for cross projects reusability with CI/CD workflow for linting and testing. The template is currently in use across multiple projects.

Steel and aluminium decarbonization

Python modeler. Developed a python library for business data analysis to optimize investment decisions in order to reduce CO2 emissions.

Agglomeration and Social Networks Research Lab

Research fellow

07/2021 - 11/2021

Urban mobility and COVID-19

Data analyst. Analyzed GPS mobility data to provide insights regarding the impact of COVID-19 in the urban mobility of Budapest.

Cities Observatory (ITESM)

Data and network science consultant 05/2020 - 11/2021

Accesibility and mobility analysis

Project manager & Data analyst. Coordinate with the data science team the development of a methodology to measure urban accessibility in 75 Mexican cities using open data. The findings are currently being used to lobby local governments to improve the urban conditions.

Air quality during COVID-19 pandemic lockdown

Project manager. Coordinated a team of researchers to design and develop a methodology to measure the changes in air quality for the cities of Mexico City, Guadalajara, and Monterrey during the COVID-19 lockdowns.

LAC_analytics

Co-founder

01/2020 - 11/2021

City Intelligence

Project manager & Developer. Coordinated the development of a data-driven web platform and API for the analysis of cities and amenities. Some applications of the platform and the data are: location intelligence for real estate, traffic, and public transport, and the analysis of the urban mobility of the city.

Evaluation of air quality and urban environment

Data analyst. Analysis and data visualization for air quality data in the area where a new public transport system is being built. This project was a collaboration within multiple actors, including Google.org, and the Government of Jalisco.

Central European University

Ph.D. Researcher 08/2017 - 11/2021

Multimodal Fingerprint of Urban Transportation Networks

Data scientist & analyst. Development of computational methods for the analysis of urban form in multiple cities. The methods were used to identify patterns in urban mobility infrastructure, and to provide insight on the future of the cities.

Bicycle infrastructure network analysis

Data scientist & analyst. Research and design of algorithms to evaluate and improve the connectivity of bicycle infrastructure networks. The algorithms where applied to fifteen different cities in the world, and the results were published in the journal Royal Society Open Science.

Quantifying life quality as walkability

Data scientist & analyst. Analysis of pedestrian urban accessibility metrics to quantify the liveability of a given city. The project was developed for the Budapest municiaplity as part of a strategy to dectect oportunities around the city and to develop data-driven public policies.

Signa_Lab

Executive Coordinator 08/2016 - 08/2017

Online social networks analysis

Project manager & Data analyst. I coordinated the research and development of methodologies to analyze social media data (Twitter, Facebook, and Youtube) to identify patterns and trends in online political conversation.

Mesura

Networks Analyst 10/2015 - 08/2017

Online social networks analysis

Data analyst. Worked with multinational clients to analyze and improve their social media presence. I developed tools to automatize the data collection with the use of APIs.

IMTJ (Mobility Institute of the State of Jalisco)

Analyst

1/2014 - 10/2014

Sustainable urban mobility

Public policy analyst Worked with a team of urban and mobility planners to develop the public policies and technical specifications for the operation of the first bike share system in Guadalajara, Jalisco. México.

Colectivo Triciclo

Co-Founder, Principal Architect 8/2010 - 1/2014

Architecture and urban design

Architect. Co-founder of my own architecture studio. I was responsible for the design of private houses and the development of urban interventions, such as a pop-up neighborhood reading kiosk.

OTHER WORK EXPERIENCE

Teaching

07/2017 - 09/2021

Python for Social Scientist

I have taught introductory Python courses for social scientists in multiple places, such as Leibniz Institute for the Social Sciences, European Consortium of Political Research, and the Central European University.

Introduction to Network Science

I have developed and taught introduction courses to Network Science for non-technical people in interdiscipliary settings. Such courses were developed to facilitate the understanding of complex systems in a friendly and interactive way.

EDUCATION

B.Arch.

Ph.D. Network Science, Central European University, Budapest, Hungary. 2021

M.A. Communication of Science and Culture, ITESO, Tlaquepaque, Mexico. 2015

Academic Visit. Center for Civic Media, MIT Media Lab, Boston, USA. 2015

Architecture, ITESO, Tlaquepaque, Mexico. 2010

Academic Visit. Universidad de Valparaíso, Valparíso, Chile. 2012

AWARDS

2020 Award for Advanced Doctoral Students. Central European University

Best lighting talk award. International Conference in Complex Networks and their

Applications.

LANGUAGES

Spanish Native

English Professional proficiency

Updated February 2022

APPENDIX

ACADEMIC PUBLICATIONS

- Natera Orozco, L. G., Battiston, F., Iñiguez, G., Szell, M. "Data-driven strategies for optimal bicycle network growth" *Royal Society Open Science*, 2020. 7: 201130. https://doi.org/10.1098/rsos.201130
- Natera Orozco, L.G., Battiston, F., Iñiguez, G., Szell, M. "Extracting the multimodal fingerprint of urban transportation networks" *Transport Findings*, 2020. https://doi.org/10.32866/001c.13171
- Natera Orozco, L. G., Deritei, D., Vancso, A., Vasarhelyi, O. "Quantifying life quality as walkability on urban networks" In: Cherifi H., Gaito S., Mendes J., Moro E., Rocha L. (eds) Complex Networks and Their Applications VIII. COMPLEX NETWORKS 2019. Studies in Computational Intelligence, 2019, pp. 905–918.
- Natera Orozco, L. G. "Un cambio de la comunicación gubernamental y política. De los medios de comunicación a las redes sociales." *Informe Anual Q Medios 2018*, edited by Bernal, G. Jalisco, Mexico: ITESO.
- Natera Orozco, L. G., Reguillo, R. "Comunicación y cambio social: participación política e internet en Jalisco" *Enciclopedia Jaliscience de la Comunicación.*, edited by Orozco, G., Reguillo, R. Jalisco, Mexico: Universidad de Guadalajara.
- Natera Orozco, L. G., (as Signa_Lab) "Battle of the hashtags: Mapping the online conversation surrounding Mexico's gas price" *Global Voices*.
- Natera Orozco, L. G. "Comunicación, ciudad e internet: flujos de información urbana en entornos digitales" VI Seminatio Internacional de Investigación en Urbanismo. Bogota, Colombia.

Manuscripts in Preparation and Development

- Natera Orozco, L. G., Alessandretti, L., Szell, M., Battiston, F. "Multimodal transportation and mobility in urban networks" Under review at *Transportation*
- Tupikina, L., Natera Orozco, L. G., Battiston, F. "A comparative analysis of station and dockless bike share systems."

CONFERENCE AND INVITED TALKS

- 2021 *Invited talk:* Bauhaus-Universität Weimar, Germany.
- 2021 *Invited talk:* URBANUM. Budapest, Hungary.
- 2021 *Invited talk:* Graph data science. Manning Publications.
- 2020 *Invited talk:* Science, Technology and Innovation Council. Hidalgo, Mexico.
- 2020 *Invited talk:* Neo Urban Networks Workshop. Paris, France.
- 2020 *Invited talk:* PIP Ciudad Futuro. Guadalajara, Mexico.

2019 Conference: VIII Conference in Complex Networks and their Applications. Lisbon, Portugal. 2019 Invited talk: Data Science MeetUp. Timisoara, Romania. 2019 *Invited talk:* FabLab, West University of Timisoara, Timisoara, Romania. 2019 Conference: Cycling Research Board Meeting. Delft, Netherlands. 2019 Invited talk: 4D Cities, Multi-Actor Systems Department, TU Delft. Delft, Netherlands. 2019 *Invited talk:* Mobile and Social Computing Lab, Fondazione Bruno Kessler. Trento, Italy. 2019 *Conference:* The Network Science Society Conference. Burlington, USA. 2019 Invited talk: ANET-Talks, ANET Lab, Hungarian Academy of Science. Budapest, Hungary. 2018 Invited talk: Signa_Lab, ITESO. Tlaquepaque, Mexico. 2018 Conference: SICC Workshop ComplexCity@PoliTo. Turin, Italy. 2015 Invited talk: Encuentro de Urbanismo Alternativo, Centro Cultural de España en México. Mexico City, Mexico. 2015 Invited talk: II Simposio de ciudades y territorios incluyentes "Derecho a la Ciudad", Universidad Autónoma de Yucatán. Merida, Mexico. 2013 Conference: Future of Places. Stockholm, Sweden.

GRANTS AND FELLOWSHIPS

Write-up grant. Central European University
Registration grant. International Conference in Complex Networks and their Applications
Ph.D. conference travel grant. CEU Budapest Foundation
Registration grant. NetSci
Travel grant. Department of Network and Data Science, Central European University
Doctoral grant. Central European University.
Academic Stay at MIT. Mexican National Council of Science and Technology
Master Studies Grant. Mexican National Council of Science and Technology

DETAILED TEACHING EXPERIENCE

GESIS – Leibniz Institute for the Social Sciences

Introduction to Computation Social Sciences with Python. GESIS Fall Seminar in Computational Social Science. Co-taught with Orsyola Vásárhelyi

European Consortium for Political Research

Teaching Assistant, Python Programming for Social Scientists. Summer Virtual Methods School 2021

2021 Teaching Assistant, Python Programming for Social Scientists. Winter Virtual Methods School 2021 Teaching Assistant, Python Programming for Social Scientists. Summer Virtual Methods 2020 School 2020 **Central European University** 2020 Teaching Assistant, Scientific Python 2019 Teaching Assistant, Statistical Methods in Network Science **ITESO** 2019 Network Science (Summer 2019) Invited lecturer, co-taught with Diego Arredondo (ITESO) 2017 Network Science (Summer 2017) Co-taught with Emma Towlson (Northeastern University), Sean P. Cornelius (Northeastern University), and Ricardo Zavala (ITESO) 2015–17 Communication, Culture and Society (Spring 2016, 2017) 2015–16 Social Systems Theory (Fall 2015, 2016)